Guide to the Rachel Rippy Collection on the Fifteenth Street School TAM.809
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rachel Rippy Collection on the Fifteenth Street School
1944-early 2000s
1964-1968
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rippy, Rachel
Theilheimer, Rachel
TAM.809
2.25 linear feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 small flat box
Rachel Winston Rippy (1930-2019) was an artist and educator dedicated to the philosphy of self-directed learning. She was born in Antwep, Belgium and emigrated to the United States in 1942. From 1964-1968, Rippy, along with her husband Wilbur, taught at the Fifteenth Street School, a free school in New York City founded by Orson Bean influenced by the Summerhill School in Suffolk, England. The Fifteenth Street School was based on the pedagogical principle of self-regulation, emphasized creativity and exploration, and classes were voluntary. Rippy later worked at the Bank Street College, advising and leading workshops for other teachers. The Rachel Rippy Collection on the Fifteenth Street School (dated 1944-early 2000s, bulk dates 1964-1968) consists of materials created and collected by Rippy documenting her and her husband Wilbur's work as teachers at the school. Materials in this collection include photographs in multiple formats, drawings by students, and original stories by students, many of which reflect current events of the time period, such as the Cold War and the Apollo space program. In additional to materials created at the time of the school's operations, this collection also includes notes, research, and writing used in the creation of the self-published 2019 book Voices of Children: The Story of the Fifteenth Street School. The collection documents not only the operations of the Fifteenth Street School, but the wider educational aims and objectives of the free school movement of the 1960s.
Scope and Contents
The Rachel Rippy Collection on the Fifteenth Street School (dated 1944-early 2000s, bulk dates 1964-1968) consists of materials created and collected by Rippy documenting her and her husband Wilbur's work as educators at New York City's Fifteenth Street School. Materials in this collection include photographs in multiple formats, drawings by students, and original stories by students, many of which reflect current events of the time period, such as the Cold War and the Apollo space program. In additional to materials created at the time of the school's operations, this collection also includes notes, research, and writing used in the creation of the self-published 2019 book Voices of Children: The Story of the Fifteenth Street School. The collection documents not only the operations of the Fifteenth Street School, but the wider educational aims and objectives of the free school movement of the 1960s.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open, with the exception of student drawings and stories in Box 4, which are restricted until 2044.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Rachel Theilheimer in April 2022; the accession number associated with this gift is 2022.037.
Appraisal
Five optical discs containing reproductions of physical photographs in the collection were appraised out of the collection.
Biographical Note
Rachel Winston Rippy (1930-2019) was an artist and educator dedicated to the philosphy of self-directed learning. She was born in Antwep, Belgium and emigrated to the United States in 1942. From 1964-1968, Rippy, along with her husband Wilbur, taught at the Fifteenth Street School, a free school in New York City founded by Orson Bean influenced by the Summerhill School in Suffolk, England. The Fifteenth Street School was based on the pedagogical principle of self-regulation, emphasized creativity and exploration, and classes were voluntary. Rippy later worked at the Bank Street College, advising and leading workshops for other teachers.
Free schools; Education -- Study and teaching.; Education -- Aims and objectives; School management and organization.; Education -- Experimental methods; Educational change -- New York (N.Y.); Theilheimer, Rachel
- Book Drafts, circa early 2000s (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
- Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Original Storybooks by Wilbur Rippy, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
- The New Yorker, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Photographs, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2-9, Box 3, Folder 1-6)
- Photographs and Contact Sheets, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Contact Sheets, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Photographic Slides, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Children's Drawings, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  This folder is restricted until 2044.
- Children's Stories, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)